This video describes how to perform direct ophthalmoscopy.
Start with hand hygiene and introduce yourself.
Confirm the patient's identity, then explain the examination and gain consent to perform it.
Take a few seconds to observe the peri-orbiter, eye-lens and
the eyes themselves, commenting on any positive or relevant negative
findings.
The next step is to perform the fundal reflex test to assess for mediopacity.
Set the arc light by clicking the button three times for the brightest light,
and then move the lens rack to the top so there's no lens power.
With the arc light prepared, dim the lights in the room, and at arm's
length, look through the
sight hole.
Ask the patient to look at the light, observing both eyes at the same time.
The light should reflect from the fundus, back through the pupils, looking symmetrically bright
with similar colour.
Any asymmetry suggests an abnormality such as corneal scar, cataract,
blood in the vitreous or a retinal tumour.
Next, examine the back of the eye.
Ask the
patient to fix on a target in the distance.
Use your right hand and right eye to examine
their right eye and your left for their left.
Start with your feet close to the patient and
lean back.
Identify the fundal reflex and follow this moving in on a path 10 to 15 degrees
temporal on the horizontal.
When you're close to the eye, the optic
disc should come into view.
Go in closer still and you'll get a wider and more stable view.
Comment on how distinct the margin of the disc is, the colour of the
new retinal rim and the
cup to disc ratio.
Then look for other signs along the four major branches of the retinal
vessels.
Finish by asking the patient to look into the light to bring the centre of the
macula called the phobia interview.
In a non-dilator dye, this will cause the
pupil to constrict and you will lose the view.
In a dilated pupil, the phobia can
be seen as a slightly darker zone with a pinpoint reflection.
Repeat this
examination on the other eye.
After the examination, thank the patient
summarise your findings and repeat hand hygiene.
Please have a look at our other
University of St Andrews Art Flight project videos.